This is a work of fiction. Names, characters,
places and incidents either are products of the
author’s imagination or are used fictitiously. Any
resemblance to actual events or locales or
persons, living or dead, is entirely coincidental.
世界を救う戦いだと誰かが言った
お前たちに　全人類の希望が懸かっていると誰かが言った
Somebody said that this is a fight the fate of the world hinges upon.
カウント　スリー　ツー　ワン　リフトオフ
Somebody said that the fate of
mankind rests on our shoulders.
でも　俺にとってそんなことは興味なくて
Countdown!
3! 2! 1!
レーザー光銃座　サンダーエンペラーに
Liftoff!
But I really don't care about things like that.
えっと　積み込み済みだよ
Laser gun support, um... loaded onto the Thunder Emperor.
システムリンク　オンライン
ポケコンを有線に
赤いケーブルね
System link online.
周辺マップ　ロード開始
Switch your PokeCom to a wired connection.
It's the red cable.
3メートル　5　7
レーザースキャナー左右共に異常なし
Begin loading the area map.
10　15　20　範囲最大
3 meters! 5! 7!
No problems with the laser scanner on either side.
ちち…地形判断用AI　正常
10! 15! 20!
Maximum range.
チェックは以上
T-T-Terrain analyzer AI functional.
カイ　ぶっつけ本番だけど　いける?
最初から分かってたことでしょ
Checks done.
Kai, it's time for the main show! Are you ready?
いまさらノーゴーだなんて言わないでよ
We've planned this from the start.
カイ…
How could we back out now?
コンディション　オールグリーン
Kai...
最終判断はゴー
All conditions are green.
ガンヴァレル
The final decision is...
Go!
発進
Gunvarrel!
本字幕由諸神字幕組出品,僅供學習交流之用 更多中日雙語字幕，請登錄 www.kamigami.org
---諸神字幕組---
台本：卷
翻译:臭屁匠 苜汐瞳
校对: mam
后期:Ressul zzz
Launch!
すれ違う　言葉の裏に
閉ざされた　心の鍵
Behind the words passing by
The key to my closed heart is hidden
君という　フラグ開錠が
笑顔救えるのなら
You help me without hesitation
And if you can save my smile...
夏の風誘う　迫真のスコール
We'll listen to the call of the summer wind
波長シンクロ
Singing us a song of determination
ロマンチックみたいに　気の利いた言葉も
As we sync our wavelengths
Like in a good romance
見つからないけど　青空を目指すから
No words with an edge
Can ever reach us
We're aiming for the blue sky
僕たちは　一つになれる
戸惑いの涙も　夢も
We can become one
Our dreams and confused tears
真実に　引き寄せられるなら
Are the work of reality
それは愛しすぎる
魔法の日を
That becomes our beloved
Magical key
Because Ganvarel's waiting
IRUO. is updating.
Do not remove the battery or the memory card.
IRUO. Update
IRUO. has been updated.
Confirming voice recognition.
Please say something.
音声認識を確認します
画面に向かって　何かしゃべってください
My name is Yashio Kaito.
俺の名前は　八汐海翔
Central Tanegashima High School, regular division class 3-2.
中央種子島高校　普通科3年2組
Student number 26.
出席番号26番
Grades slightly below average.
成績は中の下
IRUO. has been updated without any problems.
居ル夫 のアップデートは問題なく完了しました
You're playing some game again?
あっ　またゲームしてる
I just updated it. There was this fun app too.
アップデートしてたの
ちょっと面白いアプリもあったしね
Nyan-Nyan, or however that goes.
にゃんにゃ～ん　なんつって
How can you be so relaxed when we're so screwed?
もうのんきだなぁ
こんなピンチのときだっていうのに
We are?
ピンチなの
We are!
ピンチだよ
Whoa, this is quite well done.
結構よくできてるな　これ
Robotics Club
The two of us are the only remaining Robotics Club members...
ロボ部はもう　うちとカイの2人しかいないんだよ
You understand that, right?
自覚してる
Yeah...
Hell, this is really well done.
ホントよくできてるなぁ
Okay, okay...
はいはい
So did you manage to catch the vice-principal?
それで　教頭はつかまったの
She's having some meeting.
また会議中だって
She's way too busy.
忙し過ぎだよ　あの教頭
And yet she tells us to hand in such a detailed breakdown list...
そのくせ　内訳書いた細かいの提出しろとか何とか
Are you still requesting the same budget?
まだあの額で部費要求するつもり
We need it after all!
だって　必要なんだもん
Central Tanegashima High School Robotics Research Club
Breakdown list for year 2019
Senomiya Akiho
There it is!
あった
You're gonna hand in the same thing again?
そのまま提出するの
Of course! Remember how he always said
そりゃそうでしょ
あの人だっていつも言ってたもん
「まだだ　まだ終わらんよ」って
"Not yet! We're not done yet!"
You aren't looking?!
あっ　見てない
We'll have to go to the staff room soon!
もう　これから職員室行かなきゃいけないのに
Can't you just go on your own?
アキちゃん　1人で行ってくればいいだろ
You're a club member too, Kai.
カイだってロボ部員なんだよ
Let's go together!
一緒に行こうじゃないか
Oh geez.
しょうがないな
Then I'll go with you, but only up until the staff room.
じゃあ　職員室の前までなら行ってあげる
Once this fight is over, that is.
この一戦が終わったらね
Huh? FRAUKOUJIRO?!
フラウ　コウジロー
Who's that?
誰
He made this game.
このゲームの作者だよ
I heard he shows up every now and then,
結構出没するとは聞いてたけど　初めて会った
but this is the first time I've seen him.
さすが
You're doing good!
With 8 frames I can deal with any attack.
8フレあれば　俺はどんな技でもつぶせるからね
I'm the fifth best in the world after all!
一応こっちは　世界5位だし
Kai, that's awesome...
カイすごいよ　作者相手に勝った
You just defeated the creator of the game!
I did justice to my fifth position.
まっ　世界５位の面目は保ったかな
New mail
What is it?
何
Sorry for the sudden msg...
It's a bit tough to say, but you see...
I suspect you of cheating, UMISHO.
Your reactions are abnormally fast. Grandma always-
lol, I mean, we've received a message saying so.
If you've anything to say about that, tell us.
A message.
メッセージだ　作者直々に
What the hell?
何言ってんだ
What's up?
どうしたの
They're saying I'm too good.
強過ぎるって
作者的にはチートでも使ってないと無理な動きしてるって
That my speeds shouldn't be possible without cheating.
チート
Cheating?
Yeah, you know, foul play.
簡単に言うと　いかさま
えっ　失礼ね　作者のくせに負け惜しみ
That's so mean!
How can the creator of the game be such a sore loser?
I'm close to the best, so of course people would say stuff out of envy,
こんだけ上位にいると
嫉妬交じりに色々言われることはあるけど
but I didn't expect that from the creator...
まさか作者がね…
You should complain!
文句言おうよ　文句
Nah, it's okay. I'm not doing anything unfair anyway.
別にいいよ
こっちはやましいことしてるわけじゃないんだし
あれ　どこ行くの
Huh? Where're you going?
職員室　行くんじゃなかったの
I thought we were going to the staff room.
Are you seriously handing this in?
これを本気で教頭に見せるのか
Yeah! You told me that's the way, Mitchie!
教頭がそう言ってたって教えてくれたのはミッチーだよ
Don't say "yeah," say "yes, sir."
「うん」じゃなくて　「はい」な
And I've told you countless times to call me Mr. Nagafukada!
あと　長深田先生って呼べって言ってるだろ
Anyway, what do you think will happen if you hand this in?
で　見せたらどうなると思う
納得していただけると思います
I think he'll accept it!
First time I've seen someone play Stingooma so aggressively...
こんなアグレッシブなスティングーマ使い　初めてだな
What should I do now?
どうしよっかなぁ
Ah, Yashio!
八汐
What?
何?
私ちょっと急いでてさ　ごみ捨て代わってくれない
I'm in a bit of a hurry here,
so could you take out the trash for me?
You're on cleaning duty too, aren't you?
あんたも掃除当番でしょ
Just give up... It's pointless to even try.
やめとけって　言っても無駄だって
But he looks like he has time.
でも　暇そうじゃん
Sure, I can do that for you.
そうだな　代わってもいいよ
Really?
ホント
If you can defeat me in Kill-Ballad,
俺に「キルバラ」で勝てたらね
I'll take out the trash and do anything else you say too.
そしたら　ごみ捨てでも何でもするよ
I told you...
ほら　言ったろ
Let's go.
行こうぜ
What's wrong with him?
何よ　あいつ
Was the vice-principal in?
教頭は　いた?
Nope. I left it with Mitchie.
いなかったから　ミッチーに預けてきた
Mitchie? Are you sure that's a good idea?
ミッチー　大丈夫なの
Well, he's our adviser, you know.
一応ロボ部の顧問だし
大丈夫　ちゃんと渡したか後で問い詰めるから
It should be fine.
I'll make sure he gave it to the vice-principal later.
Whoa... I'll call you Aki the Turtle.
すごいね　スッポンアキちゃんと呼んであげよう
Huh? Is that supposed to make me feel goo-
何それ　うれしくな…
Ah!
やあ　やあ　日高君
Long time no see, Hidaka!
It's already been a year and three months since we met.
ここで会ったが　1年と3カ月目
It's still not too late to join the Robotics Cl-
今からでも遅くはないから　ロボ部に入って一緒に…
I refuse.
お断りします
Consider it!
ばっさり
I've considered it enough the 20 times you asked me before.
ばっさりも何も　20回以上そう答えたはずです
Don't talk to me, please.
もう僕に話し掛けないでください
But... wait!
でもほら　ロボ部には日高君の技術力が必要だし
We need your skills in the Robotics Club!
楽しいよ　ロボ部
It's fun!
汗と油にまみれて　みんなで協力して１つのものを造る
We build stuff and try our best together!
そして　夕日に向かって走るんだよ
We head towards the sunset!
Leave me the hell alone!
ついてこないでください
But...
Excuse me.
失礼します
I won't give up until I make him join!
あいつ　絶対ロボ部に入れてやるんだから
But he hates you so much...
あんなに嫌われてるのに　さすがスッポンアキちゃん
You're really Aki the Turtle!
It's your problem too, you know!
だから　人ごとじゃないでしょー
How are you feeling?
体調は
No worries.
うん　平気
You're heading straight home?
真っすぐ帰る
You wanna go somewhere?
どっか寄りたいの
ハンガー寄りたいなぁって思ってるんだけど
I wanted to drop by the hangar...
Oh right...
そっか
It's important that we take care of it!
ほら　やっぱり整備は大事でしょ
これからのロボ部としても…
For the future of the Robotics Club and-
あっ　カイ　一緒に来てよ
Kai!
Come with me!
Open Sesame!
ハッチ　開け
Why do you say that every time?
何でいちいち言うの
It's important to set the mood.
こういうのは気分が大切なの
We should clean this place sometime...
一度大掃除しないとね
So? Is it still here?
大丈夫　なくなったりしてない
Of course it is.
なくなるわけないでしょ
It's the fruit of the Robotics Club's hard work.
ロボ部の　汗と涙の結晶なんだから
The project to build a working copy of the giant Robot of Justice, Gunvarrel.
正義の巨大ロボ　ガンヴァレルの実物大を造ろうプロジェクト
We abbreviate it as GunPro.
略してガンつくは　ロボ部が創設したときに始まり
It all started when the Robotics Club was founded,
and using an abandoned airport hangar, it still continues little by little to this day.
閉鎖された空港の格納庫を間借りして
今でも　こつこつと続けているプロジェクトだ
I'm not so sure if it's possible to finish it before we graduate,
卒業までに完成できるかも怪しい状態だが
but Aki believes that we'll succeed.
それでも　アキちゃんは間違いなく完成すると信じている
Good morning, Gunvarrel.
おはよ　ガンヴァレル
Let's see, what else was there?
後は…ここも　と
Phew, it gets so stuffy this time of the year...
この季節になると蒸すよねぇ
Help!
手伝え　これは警告などではない
This is no idle threat!
Resist and I'll shoot!
抵抗すれば撃つ
Finishing move! Gunvarrel Ankh Striker!
必殺　ガンヴァルアンクストライカー
Ba-ba-ba-bang!
What's wrong?
どうかした
I just got oil all over myself.
油が垂れてきただけ
You alright?
平気?
Don't! Come! Closer!
ちょ…こら　来んな
Kicking just lifts your skirt even more.
大キックは隙が大きいから　逆に見えるよ
I'll kill you if you look.
見たら　怒るからね
What were you doing?
カイは何してたの
Somehow it feels like time left this place behind.
何か　こうしてると
この場所は　時間から取り残されてるみたいだなぁって
Or is that too girly for me to say?
なんて　ちょっと少女趣味過ぎるか
That's why the weirdos who actually come here
だからこそ　ここにいる変わり者同士
should work together for the sake of the club.
手を取り合って　部のために協力するんだよ
ねっ?
Right?
If you can defeat me in Kill-Ballad, I'll help you.
「キルバラ」でアキちゃんが勝てたら　協力してあげるよ
The Power Suit company EXOSKELETON aims to develop
エグゾスケルトン社　パワードスーツは
products even closer to people than cars or PokeComs, and-
自動車　ポケコンと同じようにより身近に…
Incoming call
Accept call. Voice only.
電話　受信　音声のみ
Incoming call
End call
Hey, Kai!
カイ
Huh? Why voice only?
あれ　何で音声だけ?
I'm getting dressed.
着替え中
Oh, okay.
そっか
Anyway, have you done the English homework for tomorrow?
あのさ　あした提出の英語の宿題　やった?
やってないよね
You haven't, right?
Why do you assume that?
何で決め付けるかな
やってないけど
I haven't, though.
Figured.
だよね　ねえ分担しよう　分担
Hey, how about splitting the work?
He once said, "You must fight looking three steps ahead!"
あの人も　かつてこう言ってた
End call
『戦いとは　常に二手三手先を読んで行うものだ』って
I doubt you're looking even just one step ahead though.
今のアキちゃんは　一手先も読めてないと思うけど
But I agree. Let's split it.
でもまあ　分担は賛成
I thought so!
End call
でしょ
じゃあ　部室いるね
I'll be waiting in the club room.
予約受け付け中です
Preorders are open now.
We wish to be the support in your life.
あなたの心の支えでありたい　エグゾスケルトン
EXOSKELETON!
Irei Store
Welcome!
いらっしゃい
Oh, it's just you?
何だ　お前か
Menthol
Where's Aki?
アキは?
I guess she went to school already.
先に　学校行ったんじゃないかな
She dares to ignore me?
あいつ　私をスルーするとはいい度胸だね
I don't think she's ignoring you, Mizuka.
まさか　瑞榎さんをスルーするつもりなんてないですよ
She just has no money.
お金がないだけ
Tell Mitchie to come and pick up his proteins already.
ミッチーに言っといて
プロテイン　とっとと取りに来いって
Why don't you call him and tell him yourself?
直接言えばいいのに　電話で
めんどい
It's a pain.
More like, I don't wanna talk to him.
つーか　しゃべりたくない
それは　俺も同じなんだけど
Neither do I.
What?!
なに　忘れていた
I forgot about it! And I don't have any cash on me today!
しかも　今日は金がない
You need an umbrella when talking with him...
唾が飛ぶ　だから嫌なんだよなぁ
This is why I didn't want to do it.
I've told you, anyway.
伝えましたからね
じゃあ
Was she mad?
伊禮は怒っていたか
Who knows? I'd say she was.
さあ　でも…たぶん怒ってたんじゃないかなぁ
いいか　八汐　伊禮瑞榎を怒らせるとマジ怖い
Listen, Yashio!
Nothing's worse than making Irei Mizuka angry!
Remember that!
これ　豆知識な
I know.
知ってる
Then let me tell you one more thing! Listen closely!
じゃあ　もう1つ教えてやるよく聞け
Oh man...
Energetic strike
疾風怒濤の
with the speed of lightning!
元気一発
Gunvarrel!
ガンヴァレル
Yay!
You'll break your PokeCom again if you keep jumping around in this tiny space.
こんな狭い所で暴れると　またポケコン壊すよ
Wee, Skal!
スコール
I talked with Mitchie at the school gates.
校門のとこでミッチーと話しててさ…
Huh? What's this anime?
何　そのアニメ
It's Gunvarrel! You know, Gunvarrel!
『ガンヴァレル』だよ　『ガンヴァレル』
Ah, okay.
ああ　そうだった
"Okay"?!
「そうだった」?
Don't you know what your Kill-Ballad game is based on?
あのね　カイがしょっちゅうやってる『キルバラ』は何のゲーム?
『ガンヴァレル』
Gunvarrel.
What are we working so hard on in this club?
うちの部が　一生懸命造ってるのは?
ガンヴァレル
Gunvarrel.
What's this anime?
このアニメは?
Gunvarrel.
『ガンヴァレル』
Fine. You scared me there for a second.
よろしい
もう　びっくりしたよ
腰が抜けるかと思ったよ
Let me explain once more then.
じゃあ　もう一度説明してあげるね
No need... It's long too.
いや…いいよ　長いし
駄目
No!
You already know that our current robot boom is mostly because of Gunvarrel.
あのね　今のロボットブームは
全て『ガンヴァレル』が引き金になっていると言っていいの
It's a monumental work: a compilation of half a century of Japanese mecha anime.
日本ロボットアニメの半世紀にもわたる集大成にして　金字塔
It was broadcast in 168 countries around the world. It's insanely popular.
世界168カ国で放送され　世界的にも大人気
And still, the last episode was canceled.
にもかかわらず　最終回はまさかの放送中止
Gunvarrel Ankh Strike!
ガンヴァルアンクストライカー
Four years have passed since then, but the last episode is still a mystery.
あれから4年たった今も　最終回は謎のまま
Its contents must be something truly divine...
その内容は　神の出来であろうことは間違いなく…
Oh, right.
あっ　そうだ
What?
何?
Clean
the
clubroom!!
Don't
forget
to turn
off the
lights!
さっき　ミッチーに言われたんだ
Mitchie told me earlier that the vice-principal's gonna visit us during lunch break.
昼休み　教頭が会ってくれるって
嘘
No way...
ホント
It's true.
Staff Room
The time has come!
時は来た
ほら　カイも気合入れて
Kai, show some spirit!
ねえ　俺も行かなきゃ駄目?
Do I really have to come too?
Of course! You're a member of the Robotics Club too!
当たり前でしょ　カイもロボ部なんだから
今日　ここに呼ばれた理由は分かってますか
Do you know why I called you here today?
Yes! It must be about our club budget!
はい　部費の件ですよね
Thank you for making your decision!
ようやく決断してもらえたみたいで
ありがとうございます
どうやら　まだ頭は冷めていないようですね
It would seem you are still hot-headed.
Now, regarding this absurd demand that you consider reasonable.
では　あなたが正当だと考えるこの非常識な部費の請求理由について
Central Tanegashima High School Robotics Research Club
Breakdown list for year 2019
Senomiya Akiho
Would you tell me more about this again?
あらためて聞きましょうか
Oh please, I've told you so many times already!
いやだなぁ
それは　もう何度も話しましたよ
「あらためて」と言っているのです
I said, tell me about it again.
来年の2月に東京万博が開かれ　世界中のロボットが集まります
Next February the Tokyo World Expo will be opened, and robots from throughout the world will gather.
So that our club can present a giant robot there as a regular exhibitor,
わが部は　その一般参加の部に
巨大ロボットで出場するために
半年でロボットを完成させねばならず
and to complete the robot in half a year,
we need the budget detailed in the document!
部費がそれだけ必要となるわけです
It's over...
終わったな
But that has not changed whatsoever from before.
それじゃあ　以前と何も変わってませんよ
The detailed budget request is exactly the same as well.
この内訳も前と同じです
当然です
Of course!
Does it really have to be a giant robot?
そもそも　巨大ロボットである必要があるんですか
The GunPro1 is the product of the Robotics Club's hard work!
ガンつく1は　ロボ部の汗と涙の結晶
It's our dream to take it to the Expo!
あの子を万博に持っていくのが　うちの夢なんです
On that we can't yield an inch!
これだけは譲れません
じゃあ　質問を変えます
Then let me change my question.
Can the two of you even complete such a giant thing?
2人でそんな大きいもの　完成させられるのですか
In a mere 6 months?
しかも　半年で
そこは根性で
We'll do whatever it takes!
That is not an answer.
話になりません
She just doesn't want to accept the indiscretions of youth.
認めたくないものだな　若さ故の過ちというものを
アキちゃん　何やってんの
What are you doing, Aki?
Very well. I'll set a condition.
分かりました
条件を出しましょう
A condition?
条件…ですか
Eight years ago, your sister showed results
8年前　あなたのお姉さんは結果を出して
and turned a gathering into a club.
同好会を部へと昇格させた
Show me some results.
あなたも結果を出しなさい
そしたら　この無謀な部費も考えてあげましょう
If you can do that, I shall consider this absurd budget.
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much!
Wait!
待ちなさい
I have not told you the condition yet.
私は　まだ何の条件も出してませんよ
Are you listening?
いいですか
条件は次のとおりです
The condition is as follows...
I'm on fire! I'm on fire! I'm on fire!
たぎってきた　たぎってきた　たぎってきた
Let's do this, Kai!
やるよ　カイ
Do you seriously believe we can do it?
本気でできると思ってるの
できるよ
Of course!
We only have to win the Robo-One!
ROBO－ONEで優勝でしょう
Our club won it eight years ago too!
8年前　うちの部は優勝してんだから
Sure, after they spent a year researching in preparation.
当時も1年近く研究して優勝したって聞いたよ
We only have two weeks until this year's tournament.
今年の大会まで2週間しかないんだけど
We can overcome time with determination!
時間は　やる気でカバー
Since the robot boom, there are more people participating,
ロボットブームで参加者は増えてるし　技術も高度になってる
and the technology's advanced a lot as well.
We have the willpower!
そこは根性で
But if we can't win, the club will be disbanded.
しかも優勝できなかったら　即刻廃部
Don't consider losing before the battle!
勝負の前に　負けることは考えない
First of all, do we have a hobby robot?
それ以前に　ホビーロボットあるの
ど…どうしよう
What should we do?
You just noticed?
今　気付いたの
Wait, no!
って駄目　駄目
My only virtue is that I'm stupidly positive!
うちは　無駄に前向きなのが唯一の取りえなんだから
何とかなる　何とかする
It'll work out somehow! We'll do it somehow!
ガンヴァレルが　待ってるから
Gunvarrel's waiting for us!
Numbered Report 2887:
ナンバー2887を　お伝えします
The current year is 2019, June 13th. 19:09 Japan Standard Time.
日本標準時　西暦　2019年6月13日　19時9分現在
Situation remains unchanged.
状況には　変化がありません
Whose eyes are those eyes?
その目　だれの目?
幼い思い出　眩しい波光に
The blinding light of childhood memories
夢に見た景色は
Turns the scenery of my dream
Into monochrome as it lies forgotten
置き忘れたまま
モノクロになって
瞳から消える
And vanishes from my eyes
だけどいつでも君は
But you've always been
まっすぐ明日を見つめた
Looking straight at the future
どれくらいの涙と引き換えに
And you paid the price in tears
だから僕らの迷いも
So we turn our hesitation
強さに変えてくれる
Into strength by the power
Of our connected hearts
繋がった心が解き放つ
Feel it! These overflowing emotions
不意に溢れ出す思い
For that someone in the sunset
同じに誰かのために
I'll use the little courage I have
この小さな勇気で
風が吹き荒れても
And overcome the rage of the wind
Because I want to protect you
君を守りたくて